# (Robert) Cameron Rutherford HPC/ML/Q Research Software Engineer

 ♠ Manhattan, NY
 ☑ cameron.rutherford@me.com
 ☑ (509) 218-1818

Cameronrutherford in Robert C Rutherford

### Summary

High Performance Computing (HPC) / Machine Learning (ML) / Quantum (Q) Research Software Engineer (RSE) with over 3 years of experience deploying, testing, optimizing and teaching people about scientific software and computing systems. I have worked on a wide variety of projects during my time at "the lab", and have had my code run on everywhere from the largest supercomputer in the world, to a novel quantum computer.

#### **Skills**

C / C++17 CMake, Spack, CUDA / HIP RAJA + Umpire / Kokkos MPI, pybind11, toml11, spdlog **Python** Pytorch, JAX, Distributed ML conda, poetry, mamba quarto, nbdev, qiskit

**DevOps** Docker, ghcr, S3 Singularity/Apptainer, charliecloud, podman GitHub, GitLab, pre-commit

### **Experience**

2020 - Present Software Engineer HPC/ML/Q, Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (Virtual)

- Lead Software Stack for ExaSGD project through key Frontiner deployment to 8k nodes and 54k GPUs
- MLOps internal offering lead developing containerisation and best practices community
- On-boarding and support experience for both HPC Clusters and IBMQ systems
- Deployed ML software stack for various projects, and assisted in building continuous integration pipelines
- Lead Privacy Preserving ML project to explore FHE, FL, DP and SMC

Sports Events Coordinator, Whitworth University (Spokane, WA)	2019 - 2020
IT Intern, Mac Management, Keysight Technologies (Colorado Springs, CO)	2018
Calculus III Grader / Mathematics Tutor, Whitworth University (Spokane, WA)	2017, 2019
Basketball Coach, S.G.S. & M.L.C (Sydney, AUS)	2015

#### **Publications**

- S. Abhyankar, S. Peles, R. Rutherford, A. Mancinelli, Evaluation of AC optimal power flow on graphical processing units. (IEEE PESGM 2021)
- S. Peles, M. Alam, A. J. Mancinelli, K. Perumalla, R. C. Rutherford, J. Ryan, C. G. Petra, Porting the Nonlinear Optimization Library HiOp to Accelerator-Based Hardware Architectures (arxiv 2021)

#### **Conferences**

Practice and Experience in Advanced Research Computing (PEARC)	2023
Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL) Tech Fest	2021-2023
Energy Exascale Earth System Model (E3SM) Annual Meeting	2023
Sustainable Tools Ecosystem Project (STEP) East Coast Town Hall	2023
Exascale Computing Project (ECP) Annual Meeting	2021-2023
Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL) Innovation Summit	2022
Co-Design Centre for Quantum Advantage (C2QA) Annual Meeting	2022

## **Education**

Scientist & Engineer Rising Leader Learning Journey	2023
Cyber Security & National Security Seminar Series, PNNL	2021 - 2022
Whitworth University, B.S. Mathematics and Computer Science	G.P.A 3.9/4.0
<ul> <li>Outstanding Mathematics Major 2020</li> <li>ICPC Pacific Northwest Eastern Washington Site Winner 2018</li> <li>Howard R. Gage Memorial Scholarship 2017, 2018, 2019</li> </ul>	

# **Other Activities**

Sustainable Horizons Institute HPC Mentor	2022, 2023
Quantum Information Science / HPC STEM Mentor	2022 - Present
Whitworth Chess Club President	2019 - 2020
Pine Codes Hackathon Winner	2019
SpokAnimal Shelter Volunteer	2019
Whitworth Men's Basketball Team	2016 - 2019